[Music]
a series of articles published in the
annals of internal medicine culminated
in a recommendation suggesting people
keep eating their red and processed meat
nutrition researchers savaged these
articles the chair of nutrition at
harvard called it a very irresponsible
public health recommendation and the
past harvard nutrition chair was even
less restrained
it's the most egregious abusive data
i've ever seen said walt willett they're
just layers and layers of problems
let us start to pick through these
layers
first of several serious weaknesses was
that the analyses and recommendations
were largely based on the so-called
grade criteria
which i talked about in my last video
the authors aired in applying the grade
tools since that was designed for drug
trials
grade automatically scores observational
studies as low or very low scores for
certainty of evidence
which is exactly what you want when
you're evaluating evidence from drug
trials you want a randomized
double-blind placebo-controlled trial to
prove the drugs risks and benefits
however the infeasibility for conducting
randomized clinical trials on most
dietary lifestyle and environmental
exposures makes the criteria
inappropriate in these areas since it
would involve controlling people's daily
diet and following them for decades
you can't do a double-blind
placebo-controlled trial of red meat and
other foods on heart attacks or cancer
for dietary and lifestyle factors it's
impossible to use the same standards for
drug trials like imagine telling one
group of people to smoke a pack of
cigarettes every day for the next 20
years to prove that cigarettes cause
lung cancer and how could you make it
double blind like have the control group
smoke placebo cigarettes
yet in the meat papers they were
downgrading studies due to lack of
blinding well duh i mean in nutrition
trials how are you going to blind people
to the fact of what they're eating
grade is just the wrong tool for diet
studies in fact the authors admit that
the reason their recommendations differ
from all the others is that other
guidelines have not used the great
approach and the reason is you can't
randomize people to smoke avoid physical
exercise breathe polluted air or eat a
lot of sugar or red meat and then follow
them for 40 years to see if they die
now that doesn't mean you have no
evidence it just means you have to look
at the evidence in a more sophisticated
way and alternative approaches to great
exist like for example nutrigrade which
have specifically been developed to
evaluate evidence from studies of
nutritional and lifestyle factors
so are the authors appeals to standards
of evidence motivated by a genuine
interest in getting to the bottom of it
or just to advance the financial
interests of industry as the same lead
author had done previously at the behest
of soda and candy companies the tool he
employed in his meat and sugar studies
could be misused to discredit all sorts
of well-established public health
warnings like the link between
secondhand smoke and heart disease air
pollution and health problems physical
inactivity and chronic disease or trans
fats
industries could use it to sow doubt in
any field where randomized controlled
trials are not feasible such as climate
change
what are you going to have some placebo
planet
strict adherence to grade guidelines
could even be used to question the link
between smoking and lung cancer
i know you can't randomize people to
smoke but can't you randomize people to
quit
a randomized controlled trial of the
effect on aged men of advice
to stop smoking of those randomized to
quit 13.7 died within the study window
whereas of those in the control group
who got no special instruction only 12.9
percent died
in other words it didn't work
disappointingly the researchers
concluded we find no evidence at all of
any reduction in total mortality
wait so is smoking not bad for you after
all of course not
anyone see the fatal flaw
they didn't randomize people to quit
they randomized people to advice to quit
smoking right it's not like they could
lock people in a room for a few years at
last follow up the stop smoking group
was smoking eight cigarettes a day
compared to 12 cigarettes a day in the
control group so no surprise there was
no difference in mortality since there
was hardly any difference in smoking and
the same thing with diet there have been
massive randomized dietary trials the
women's health initiative the multiple
risk factor intervention trial that
wasted hundreds of millions of dollars
because people just flat out failed to
follow the dietary advice so the groups
ended up eating similar diets at the end
so had similar disease outcomes
just like the randomized smoking quit
trial
and it's not like the failure was a
result of inexperienced investigators
these trials were conducted by some of
the very best research teams who
invested enormous efforts to achieve
their goals but it just shows you can't
really run decade long randomized trials
that require changes in eating behavior
people just won't do it
randomized controlled trials couldn't
even show an effect on mortality of
smoking which is pretty remarkable
considering that smoking is one of the
most powerful known risk factors in the
world so basically the foregone
conclusion putting any kind of junk to
the test in this matter would echo the
new meat report conclusion that people
should eat whatever they want and do
whatever they want
it's like a hijacking of evidence-based
medicine of course we want the best
evidence possible but the whole process
is now being manipulated and misused to
support subverted or perverted agendas
it's very exciting and attention
grabbing to say there's no need to
reduce meat intake it's less exciting to
say we reviewed studies to evaluate the
validity using a system not meant to
evaluate the validity of these studies
and what we found is nothing
when asked whether physicians can advise
persons whether a salad
is healthier than a bowl full of sugar
one of the senior co-authors of the meat
papers responded that physicians should
tell persons that the quality of
evidence is low so it depends almost
entirely on their preferences
when grade criteria do not allow us to
strongly recommend against smoking a
cigarette with your bowl of sugar
we believe that alternative grading
systems are preferable
[Music]
you